so this is a the suta geriman understood
again and one of the perceptions that need to
and one of the perceptions that need to
be developed
what is the perception of dispassion
and there's also the the perception of
cessation but
it's said in the same way it's described
the same way
dispassion and cessation
here biku having gone into seclusion
reflects this is peaceful this is
sublime that is the stilling of all sankara's
that is the stilling of all sankara's
activities the relinquishing of all
acquisitions the relinquishing of all acquisitions
the relinquishing of all acquisitions
the destruction of craving dispassion
ibana so this so this
this
type of perception can only
start being developed
after many others have been developed
it's not something that you can
it's also it seems like more of a result
well yes it's the result
this passion is a result that then at
some point you know when your mind has
sufficiently developed you recognize
that as well
you recognize this passion as a direct
result as a phenomenon that's the result
of
all previous efforts and now you can
single that phenomenon and like amplify
it so to speak emphasize it further
that's how you kind of
develop these perceptions by recognizing them
these perceptions by recognizing them
for what they are
but you will not be able to recognize
the phenomena of this passion unless
everything else that's been leading to
this passion has been developed
beforehand right yeah you can't be
acting compassionately
thinking about
that's not that's not the perception of
this passion yeah
that's not the perception of the
religion there's a perception of the abstracted
there's a perception of the abstracted
idea yeah
so i'll just read another suitor which
seems to relate in the
in the
middle length discourse number 14
[Music] a person named mahanama
a person named mahanama
he's speaking to the buddha he says for
a long time sir i have understood your
teaching like this greed hatred and
delusion are corruptions of mind
despite understanding that sometimes my
mind is occupied occupied by thoughts of
greed hate and delusion
i wonder what qualities remain in me
that i have such thoughts
and the buddha replies there is a
quality that remains in you that makes
you have such thoughts
for if you had given up that quality you
would not still be living at home and
enjoying essential pleasures
but because you haven't given up that
quality you are still living at home and
enjoying essential pleasures
essential pleasures give little
gratification and much suffering and
stress and they are all the more full of
drawbacks even though a noble disciple has clearly
even though a noble disciple has clearly
seen this with right understanding
so long as they do not achieve the joy
and pleasure that are apart from
essential pleasures and unbeneficial
qualities or something even more peaceful than
or something even more peaceful than
that
they might still return to essential
pleasures but when they do achieve that joy and
but when they do achieve that joy and
pleasure or something more peaceful than
that they will not return to sensual
pleasures if they so so as so long as they do not
if they so so as so long as they do not
achieve the joy and pleasure that are
apart from sensual pleasures yeah and
unbeneficial yes so first thing to
mention there is uh
people can sort of uh
conclude on the basis of that paragraph
that aha so
here i am attracted to centrality
let me now find pleasure different to
centrality they will take my mind away
from centrality so let me experience the
jhana pleasure so that then my mind will not
pleasure so that then my mind will not
want to go to sensuality
if you read other suitors though the
buddha says that the only way to
experience jhana pleasure is to
completely abandon central pleasure
beforehand he said i can't remember i think
he said i can't remember i think
he said
that one can experience jhana that
developed jhana that abide in the vagina
without having thoroughly understood the
gratification danger and the escape from
sensuality that's impossible
so it's impossible to have jhana to
develop jhana to abide in jhana to
cultivatiana unless you have fully seen
developed the danger of sensuality that
perception and fully lost interest in it
and then you develop the jhana
and if that's done sufficiently enough
let's say like that
the mind will lose even any underlying
inclination to return to sensuality if
it becomes careless and falls off from
ghana so that quality needs to be developed
so that quality needs to be developed
but the only way to develop it that's
like almost like a catch-22 the only way
to develop is to first see the danger in
sexuality that's already how you develop
it so the quality that mahanama needs to
see really
most acutely is the danger in sensuality
that will then result in the quality of
pleasure different to sensuality that
then he can cultivate and not return to
central pleasures
but there are
abandoning sensual pleasures withdrawing
from them
and over time
uh you don't automatically get jonah or
uh you know but you do feel
joy well yes because you're you're free
from danger like the danger of
sensuality does not apply to you you get
the joy in the same sense you would get
the joy if you just escaped
a death trap or something
so you might not have some other
pleasure now but you certainly have
pleasure of freedom from a death trap
and that's not that's not a small thing
so that's that's what i'm saying it's
important to recognize that
you can't replace sensuality
you can't knock it out as a pack with
another pleasure that's not central
because that principle is always sensual
so even if people try to get the jhanas
and hoping that they will free them from
sensuality that will be the essential
meditation so the only way to get jhanas to
so the only way to get jhanas to
discover direction of ghana and the
wholesome pleasure that's not the
central one is to fully see the danger
of sensuality contemplate the danger
contemplate the peril of the trap and
all the hunter similes and everything
else until you absolutely mind becomes
incapable of activating towards that type of
of activating towards that type of
pleasure because of the fear of the
danger and we'll compare that to having a
and we'll compare that to having a
mental intent
directed everywhere else except to the
charcoal picked where there were two
strong men are dragging it towards
that's how you should regard sensuality
like a charcoal pit and said do you
think that man that's about to be thrown
in a charcoal pit do you think even even
like a tiny like sort of
any molecule of his being would would he
be able to to think okay no i'll go to
the chapel it's impossible he his
intention would want to be everywhere
else but there
and that's the intention there must be
cultivated towards sensual pleasures
and that's sufficiently developed that's
already a form of you know a substantial
freedom that then if you dwell secluded like
that then if you dwell secluded like
that for a while that's then the
pleasure of seclusion that's developed
beforehand that then is accompanied
later on by jhana
but so that
that pleasure of withdrawal the pleasure
of seclusion
is a pleasure
which you know which one can experience
and yeah it's a pleasure of relief
relief from the danger it's not
necessarily not necessarily a genre no no but it's
not necessarily a genre no no but it's
it's basically it's pretty accurate that
it says having been secluded from
sensuality he experiences the pleasure
and accounting that's exclusion from
sensuality and then he enters in abiding
genre so the pleasure in ghana is the
pleasure of seclusion from sensuality
not the pleasure of a mystical
experience of jainic absorption or
something so it's the pleasure of safety
the relief of safety that then if you
dwell long enough your mind will be
established in correct thinking and
pondering they will not be spilling out
into domain that doesn't pertain to
the clarity will be established the
mindfulness will be unwavering and
that's the genre on the basis of that
pleasure of seeing the danger in
sensuality and refusing to go there
anymore so so
any
a person
restrains their senses sustaining that
wild animal and it calms down
[Music] and there is a
and there is a
experience of calmness on account of
that which is peaceful which is yeah
pleasant true but it's that comes from
not being wild not not letting this
animal run wild yeah so that pleasure is
higher than essential
in that sense in a way yeah yeah because
that animal is now tamed yeah it's it's
talking it's subtler
it's utter it's higher but it's uh it's
more refined
that pleasure
of taming the animal it's more refined
but even you know so it's not it's
harder to see
that's why it takes cultivating and it
takes getting used to
and it takes time to start seeing the
true value of it
you might see the value of it when you
go really far with you know letting the
wild animal run loose and then you see
the value of peace generated by that
kind of
wild animal you created
but the thing is you want to see the
value of peace even if you don't let the
animal run wild
like that yeah there's no contrast yeah
exactly you want to not need
you want to not need
the contrast for the value of peace you
want to always see the value of peace
regardless of the contrast or the
absence of it
okay but so
even if someone's been doing that for a
long time containing that and the
animals tamed and they're not doing
anything unwholesome
unwholesome
and they haven't been wild for one year
two years
they can recognize that they are quite
calm yes yes but
they still might be attracted to
sensuality yeah so if their environment
would change or become more challenging
or something i don't know
uh the mind might revert back to you
know the pleasure that it has not
fully seen the drawbacks of and the danger in
seen the drawbacks of and the danger in
the pleasure of centrality and that's
pretty much the question you know he had
the right view there he was at least a
sodopath when he asked that question he said you
when he asked that question he said you
know a noble disciple who clearly
understood yet sometimes he still
remains attracted to this sensuality and
the mind gets clouded with sensual
desire and so on
and it's because you have not
thoroughly developed yourself in regards
to as i put us as your own body through
seeing the danger of that centrality
so when the body presents you with a
prospect of physical pleasure
three senses
your mind is not developed to withstand
it
and you develop it
like that that mind that withstanding by
contemplating the danger of of that
prospect and enduring the danger of the prospect
and enduring the danger of the prospect
and during the pull and the pain of
saying no to it
and uh not acting out of it and then
contemplating the danger and when the
danger is absent
i think like valuing the peace and the
absence of danger telling that escape
but that's what i mean it needs to be um
it needs to be taken as if your life
depends on it
that that
because if you don't take it like that
burning charcoal pit
uh
the mind will not be you know
well it won't it won't turn away from it
sufficiently enough
so the danger will not be
uh become apparent in its entirety
you might see the drawbacks you know as
an afterthought
they might keep you in check but
fundamentally you want to see the
presence of the prospect of pleasure is
the presence of peril in itself you
might feel better not two seconds later
or a millisecond later or tomorrow or if
no presence of that possibility is means
the other side of that same coin is the
peril
so then there is no touching it there is
no even for a second wanting the
charcoal burning pit
so that's important to see the
if you want to see the drawbacks of
sensuality correctly they must not be
seen as the future results of it which
they also are
you might start like that but you need
to see it as the immediate presence of
danger with the immediate presence of
possibility of pleasure that's where the
danger is
like two sides of the same coin and
that's when the danger is apparent
about the release you see you might
experience the relief
it comes from
seeing the danger
but you you shouldn't be complacent then
well sure exactly i mean you experience
the relief great and then see
okay exactly so am i still like will i in the
exactly so am i still like will i in the
future
could i in the future be still attracted
to central pleasure well okay let's wait
and see in the meantime i just have to
be very careful
value your relief
perfected guarded yeah
yeah
and another suit that
i think it might might be the same one i
think yeah i think it is
the buddha asks
again what do you think
is the king bin bisada is the king in
endowed with those five chords of
central pleasures
capable of experiencing perfect happiness joy
of experiencing perfect happiness joy
for seven days and nights without moving
his body or speaking
no he is not
what about six days and nights five four
three two one day and night
no he is not
[Music] but i am capable of experiencing perfect
but i am capable of experiencing perfect
happiness joy
pleasure for one two three four five six
seven days and nights without moving my
body and speaking
this being so who lives in the greater
pleasure the king or i
the one who has something who needs to
do something in order to get the
pleasure or the one who doesn't need to
do anything in order to abide in
pleasure who's better off the one who
doesn't need to do anything
and that's the pleasure of john
cessation of activities so
so
so the person going after central
objects essential pleasures
has to do all these activities to
maintain it to get it and so on and they
can have loads of money access loads of
access to those things
and yet
uh well as great as the pleasure might
be it always depends on the activity
yeah it depends on needing to do it
depends on duty and burden and pressure
to act and the one that doesn't
need sensual objects and essential
pleasures he gets a higher pleasure yeah he
he gets a higher pleasure yeah he
doesn't need to doesn't need to feed
maintain and it's not pressure buy
and it and it involves that
um
those that
non-involvement with those unwholesome
activities well yeah yeah it's the
result of the non-involvement with their
wholesome activities
and what about it as an encouragement
you know is it uh like they want suited
where the buddha
takes he shows one monk i think nanda his name
he shows one monk i think nanda his name
was and he takes him to these heavenly
realms it says
it says
and he shows nanda these celestial
names nymphs or whatever that are very
attractive yeah and he says which is you
know which is better
the those women on earth that you are
those women on earth that you are
attracted to
or these celestial
beings [Music] [Music]
and yeah
and then he said if you restrained from
um
if you remain celibate give up central
pleasures of worldly kind you'll get
rewarded in heaven
with these
these pleasures heavenly pleasures
i'll do that
but because he renounced those central
world essential pleasures
he went quite far became a noble
disciple and
finished the job
so he never got those
heavenly pleasures i don't think
so what's the question so is that so the
encouragement like well here is a better
pleasure well yeah yeah but again none
of that encouragement pertains to the
pleasures that you know of this world
which are entirely central pleasures
so sure if you knew if you need
uh an
encouragement of of of heavenly rewards
it's still within sensuality but it's
all within this sensuality so you would
at least remain celibate and withdrawn
but the buddha did say
that perfect celibacy basically
is not just uh being celebrated in this
life but not wanting the words of heaven
yeah that's the perfect solution yeah he
wasn't so he wasn't perfect and that's where he
so he wasn't perfect and that's where he
started feeling ashamed oh yeah and
that's why he became a noble disciple on
account of shame oh yeah because i said
oh he he's only doing this for yeah
the monks started saying well what kind
of monk this is he's just a monk because
he wants to be rewarded by name with
names in the future
and he started feeling very ashamed and
then he made the effort and became a
noble disciple and abandoned centrality
so even as an encouragement
it didn't really make him abandon
sexuality but it's the encouragement
that at least kind of enabled him to not
give up the holy life
so really as a last resort which if you
want which is he was going to do yeah he
went to the buddha to say he's going to
go back there's a servant girl or
whatever else was in the suit dimension
there that's waiting for him and
that's waiting for him and
then the buddha said well okay you know
if you don't go back these are the
pleasures they wait for you
and then okay so i'll stay because i
want the nymphs in the next life
so
he didn't become a noble disciple
account of that but he stayed a monk on
account of that
and then he felt ashamed
and dejected when he heard what other
monks are saying and then sort of made
the effort and became resolute and
abandoned it yeah
so you want giannis in this life yeah
you need to abandon principle of central
pleasure whether it's this or the next heaven
whether it's this or the next heaven
doesn't matter
you need to not want it you need to see
the parallel of it infinitely
the danger
not replace it not delay it
through and through
must be not wanted anymore
and that comes from you
and for as long as a person expects not
wanting to come out of circumstances
out of results out of prep
techniques or something it's not going
to happen
can only come out of wisdom that you
developed for yourself within yourself
so tensor strain virtue guiding the
sensors and pondering on the dangers of
those pleasures thoroughly and sorry and
thoroughly until the dangers are seen
immediately in the prospect of the
pleasure not even a second after
you feel the threat the threat is there
poisonous drink see you drink it poison
is in that agreeable drink not hey here
is the poison after when you drink that
it's the drink is the poison
so the prospect of that pleasure is the
danger how well you need to see that for
how well you need to see that for
yourself